All right, well, thank you all for your support and your encouragement and especially your
prayers, and today we get to get into God's Word one more time, so if you can open with
me to Ephesians chapter 1.
If we haven't met yet, my name is Pete, I'm one of the pastors here, and I get to preach
God's Word for us today, and I want to welcome all of you, especially if there are some of
you here that might be here for the first time today, visiting, checking things out.
Really glad that you're here and hope you have a great time just meeting with God and
getting connected with our church family here as well today.
And as we get into today's passage, I've been really enjoying this season of our church
as we've started this annual theme of higher calling, and we're focusing on that as we
go through the year of rising above temporary pursuits to live for God's eternal purposes.
And in pursuing this theme, we've been going through the book of Ephesians and just taking
a few verses at a time to go through and really try to dig into what it is that God is speaking
to us here.
We've already been talking about the inheritance that we have in Jesus Christ and things like
adoption and every spiritual blessing and forgiveness in Jesus and unity and all these
beautiful things that we've been talking about. We're going to keep digging into more of that today
as we'll tackle a few more verses in Ephesians chapter 1. And to get us started thinking about
this, of thinking about like, what does it look like when someone receives an inheritance that
completely changes their life? And so to think about this, I don't know, how many of you here
have read the book The Count of Monte Cristo by Alexandre Dumas. I see a quick show of hands. Yeah,
yeah, when I share with Building Blocks downstairs too, there was just like a couple people.
Danny and Fee had read it. No one else had read it. And I was like, okay, not so many people
reading this book. If you haven't read the book, maybe you've seen one of the almost 40 film
adaptations of this. It's been made into a movie almost 40 times, which is kind of crazy. So some
of you, maybe you've seen that, but just to give you a little bit of an overview of the story, and
I'll try not to share too many spoilers, although I am going to share the main storyline, but I would
definitely recommend reading the book or maybe checking out a movie version of it. In this book,
the story goes that there's a man named Edmond Dantes, and he has been falsely accused and
imprisoned for treason, and he's imprisoned on the island fortress of Chateau d'If, and in prison,
he meets this man named Abbe Faria, who is an elderly priest who becomes Edmond's surrogate
father and mentor. And during their imprisonment, Faria teaches Dantes things like language and
science and philosophy and history and even social manners and etiquette, basically how to be a
gentleman in that time and place. But when Abe Faria gets near to his death from a series of
strokes that he suffers, he tells Dantes how to find a secret treasure that was actually hidden in
the year 1498 by this guy named Cardinal Cesar Spada on the island of Monte Cristo. Thus we get
the name, the Count of Monte Cristo. He tells him the exact landmarks, the cave chambers, the markers,
everything that's required to locate this hidden treasure. So then what happens is that Faria dies,
and after he dies, the guards of the prison sew his body into a heavy canvas burial sack where
they're going to take his body away. But before they take his body away, they leave him for a
time. During that time, Dantes removes Faria's body from the sack and hides it somewhere else,
and then Dantes gets into that canvas burial sack and sews himself shut in it along with a hidden
knife. He knows what is going to happen, which is that thinking that they are burying the old
priest, the guards then carry that sack, and they fling it into the sea, weighed down with a cannonball.
And so Dantas is sunk under the ocean, and he then down there cuts his way out of the sack
underwater and swims to safety and freedom. Little resurrection there, okay? It's a very obvious
motif in the story. So after he gets to safety, he then reaches the island of Monte Cristo,
and there he follows Abe Faria's instructions and discovers this huge treasure trove of gold coins
and ingots and diamonds and rubies and pearls and anything else that you can imagine. He finds this
huge treasure, and then afterward he uses the near limitless wealth that he has acquired to
finance his elaborate decade-long revenge against the men who framed him, and he becomes the Count
of Monte Cristo. I'm sharing this with you, again, partly as just an example how an inheritance
could completely change somebody's life. I'm sharing this because today we are going to be
talking more about the inheritance we have received in Jesus Christ. And for us, of course,
the purpose of this is not to take revenge on somebody else for being falsely accused, far from
it. Rather, the purpose is actually to live in the full freedom and inheritance that we've received
of being adopted daughters and sons of God.
And God wants us to now live in this
in a way that completely changes our lives.
And in the same way that, you know,
a buried treasure could change a prisoner into account,
that for us, we can be transformed
from being lost children far from our heavenly father
back into close fellowship and relationship with him
into eternal life and freedom
and everything that comes with it.
And so today we're going to be reading Ephesians 1,
verse 11 through 14. I'm going to go ahead and read these verses for us. It says this,
In him we have obtained an inheritance, having been predestined according to the purpose of him
who works all things according to the counsel of his will, so that we who were the first to hope
in Christ might be to the praise of his glory. In him you also, when you heard the word of truth,
the gospel of your salvation, and believed in him, were sealed with the promised Holy Spirit,
who is the guarantee of our inheritance until we acquire possession of it to the praise of his
glory. Amen. Let me pray for us. Jesus, as we read and hear and process your word today,
we want to hear from you, God. Lord, more than wanting to hear my thoughts or from anybody else,
God, we want to hear from you. We want to hear your voice as a father speaking to his beloved
children. We want to know of what Christ has done for us. We want to know what the Holy Spirit is
doing in our lives today. We want to know you, Lord, more deeply, more fully. And we, Lord, desire
that our lives would be transformed by this inheritance that we have received in Christ,
that in fact it would change everything, that it would lead us to trust you, to find peace in you,
to find hope in you, God, but then to have boldness and courage and faith in the life that you've
called us to as well. So bless us and speak to us here today, Lord. It's in Jesus' name that we pray.
Amen. Amen. Okay, so as we look into these few verses here today, this is a fascinating passage,
and if you notice as we read through it, it has kind of two parallel lines of thought tracing
through these few verses that we want to unpack together. So we'll start with doing that, with just
trying to understand what Paul is teaching, the Ephesian church and us here today, and then
thinking and processing a bit about how does that actually change things for us? How does that
change our lives? How does that change especially the way we relate with God and trust God? That's
going to be huge as we get into today's message. And then how we respond with a life of faith. So
we're going to dig into this together. And hopefully as you read these verses, you realize
today that what we're talking about is an obtained and guaranteed inheritance. That's what these few
verses are really bringing out and putting before us here today. So let's walk through that a little
bit. If we kind of look at those parallel lines that I was mentioning earlier, you'll notice in
verse 11 and 13 that this is specifically an inheritance in Jesus. You'll notice in him,
in him. This is referring to Jesus. By the way, I'll just kind of sit on this for a second.
Those words in him, those are used eight times here in Ephesians and five times in chapter one
specifically. Also, the words in Jesus are used repeatedly in Ephesians 15 times in the letter
to the Ephesians. It says in Jesus six times here in chapter one. So, this is really important
for us to understand this. Again, I've taught before this is not just kind of a general blessing
given to the whole world, but this is a blessing and inheritance specifically given to those
who are in Christ, in Him. And so, as we think about this, we should probably be asking ourselves
questions like, am I in Jesus? And there might actually be some of you here today. You're
asking that question. Maybe you're exploring the Christian faith. You're wondering what all of this
is about. We're really glad you're here. Maybe you can wrestle with that. Am I in Jesus? Do I want to
be in Jesus? And what does it mean to be in Jesus? How does being in Jesus change my life? How does
that change my identity, my eternity, my relationships? How does that change my goals
and ambitions? And this isn't something that just happens like, oh, if you're not a Christian,
you're not, and if you kind of have this identity of Christian, all that magically happens. No,
this is very relational. This is not just some abstract idea. This is to be in Jesus means to be
in unity with Him, in love with Him, abiding in Him, trusting in Him, finding our significance in
Him, our purpose in Him, all of that to be in Him is really what Paul is hoping that the church
hears and embraces and says, I want to be in Jesus. Can you turn to somebody next to you and say,
I want to be in Jesus. All right. So, as we're reading this, who gets to be in Jesus? Who gets
to be in him? Well, you might notice here, it's we and you. Again, two parallel lines of thought,
and I want us to think about this, because notice in verse 11, it says, in him we. In verse 13,
it says, in him you. Well, who are we and you? Who is this we and this you? And sometimes we
just read through things like this, and we don't even really think about who is Paul really talking
about. And some of this will play out a little bit later in Ephesians, but just for example,
when it says in him we, it says it's we who were the first to hope in Christ. So he's probably
specifically talking about either the apostles who were the first to know and hear the gospel and
follow Jesus, or he might be talking about the Jewish believers who heard the gospel first
because it was a fulfillment of the Old Testament scriptures. Either way, this we is not just kind
of like a general we. It's actually something more specific. But then you, who is you? Well,
says, you also, when you heard the word of truth. So these are likely the Gentile believers, the
people who lived in Ephesus and had come to know Christ from hearing the gospel. These are people
who believed in Jesus a little bit later. And he's saying there's just a timeline here. There's a
difference of when these things happen. Either way, the point is actually not to separate these groups.
Ultimately, we're going to actually see how these groups come together. But either way, we find out
in verse 14, it says our inheritance. Our inheritance. So that inheritance between
whether that's the apostles and everyone else, whether it's the Jewish believers and the Gentile
believers, either way, that inheritance is actually the same. And we'll find out more about
how God brings Jew and Gentile together in chapter 2 as we study that later. But here's an amazing
thought to think about. And I think it really actually gets to the heart of what all this is
about. An amazing thought is that my inheritance and your inheritance are actually the same as
Paul's inheritance. And that's kind of crazy when you think about it. Because we think about somebody
like the Apostle Paul, and a few weeks ago we talked about his life story, everything he went
through, everything he experienced, everything he did as a follower of Jesus, all the men preaching
the gospel all over the known world, starting all these churches, writing all these books of the
Bible. Man, like Paul did a lot. And yet we find out in this passage, our inheritance and his are
the same. And for some of us, we may struggle with that thinking, but wait, I haven't done all that.
I didn't write any books of the Bible. I didn't plant any church. I didn't travel from place to
place telling people about Jesus. Man, I didn't do any of that. And this is exactly the point.
this inheritance is not something that's earned it's not something that we achieve in some way
it's given to us by the grace of God so this this is a difference here than the we and the you and
all that it's a difference in sequence but there's the same substance of it and it's similar to if
you want to go read Matthew chapter 20 you'll see there Jesus tells this parable of the laborers in
the vineyard and that one laborer is hired early in the day and works the whole day other laborers
are hired at different hours of the day up to the very end of the day, and the end of the day comes
and the master pays all of them the same, regardless of how long they've been working.
This is the grace of God. People were upset about it. They said, I deserve more, or maybe I deserve
less. But this is the grace of God, that our inheritance in him, in Jesus, is the same. We share
in that together. And so here, what is this inheritance, and how is it that we end up getting
it? Well, we find out more about that here in these verses too. First, in verse 11, we find out
this is an inheritance that has been obtained. It says, we have obtained. And just so we understand
like what's going on there, I know not many of us probably love grammar, but the grammar of that
phrase there is that it's an aorist passive indicative. You can forget those words, doesn't
matter. What it means is that this describes an action that happened in the past and is completed,
but the subject receives the action rather than performing it, okay? So if I could maybe illustrate
it to us this way, it's kind of like I've had, my family has had this happen to us a couple times
around town here in Ann Arbor where like we've been at a restaurant. Like for instance, maybe
at one time we were eating at Red Robin and we're there, we're enjoying a little dinner together
and at the end of our meal, the server comes and says, hey, your bill's already been taken care
of. Somebody else paid it for you. We're like, what? Who? And they're like, oh, somebody else
paid it for you. Somebody else wanted to pay for your meal. Oh, okay. So your bill has been paid.
Your bill's been paid, right? It's been done by somebody else. We just receive it, right? That's
what's going on here. This is an inheritance we have obtained. This is not something that Paul or
anybody else achieved. It's only received by us. It's been obtained and received by the finished
work of Jesus Christ, which we talk about all the time. We sing about all the time, but we do that
because we need it. We need to constantly remind ourselves and remind one another and sing to one
another, as the Scriptures say, sing to each other with songs and hymns and spiritual songs
to remind each other that it's not what we've obtained, not what we've done, but it is Christ
in his life, in his death on the cross for us, in his resurrection, his ascending to the Father,
that he's going to come back again. It's what he has done that has obtained this inheritance
for us. We don't achieve it. We merely receive it. This is an obtained inheritance through the work
of Christ. And we also find out in this passage that this is an inheritance that's guaranteed.
And this is happening specifically because of the work of the Holy Spirit. Now, this is important.
I think for many of us, when we think of the concept of an inheritance, we think of something
like a person's will, that at the end of their life, that they've written down a will saying,
this is who I want certain possessions to go to, whether it's financial possessions or
keepsakes or whatever else, that this is who I want these things to go to. And that's a very
appropriate parallel to what we're talking about here today, because we see that this inheritance
is sealed and guaranteed by the Holy Spirit in a very similar manner to that. To unpack that a
little bit for you, like what this means, first of all, that idea of being sealed, that's a Greek
word, sfragitso, hard to pronounce, sfragitso. And it means to use a seal to close or to make
something secure. So this would be the idea of like putting a seal on something, usually like
a wax seal to mark ownership or to sign like a signature, to like sign a letter with a seal
saying this is the person who this letter is from to denote approval or also even to close something
and make it secure that it can't be opened, to put a seal on something. So the same word is used
actually with the sealing of Jesus' tomb, okay, by the Roman guards, putting a seal on something.
So here, this is an inheritance that is sealed by the Holy Spirit and also guaranteed.
The Greek word there is araban, and this is the first or initial payment of money or assets
as a guarantee for the completion of a transaction or pledge.
So you could think about this when you put a down payment on something, maybe like a
car or a house or something like that.
By the way, don't use all those weird installment plan things, the Klarna, all that stuff.
Don't use that, okay?
But just imagine that you're putting like a down payment on something as a guarantee that you're going to finish that out.
A guarantee, okay?
That is the kind of guarantee here.
So now as we understand this, you were sealed with the promised Holy Spirit.
And that it's the Holy Spirit who is the guarantee of our inheritance, that down payment.
Well, now we understand the seal of the Holy Spirit is the guarantee that we will receive the fullness of our inheritance in Christ.
is we've received the down payment,
the Holy Spirit sealing, dwelling now within us,
always with us.
We've received that down payment.
The fullness, the completion of it
is gonna come later in God's heavenly kingdom.
All this happens for two reasons
as we unpack this passage.
The first of those reasons
is that it's predestined according to God's will.
The second way that it happens
is you heard and believed the gospel.
And I love it.
Paul just keeps pushing these things.
at us, doesn't he? We've been talking about this the last couple weeks, wrestling with it. Some of
us, we struggle with this idea that in this, two things are true at the same time. Two things are
true at the same time, that it is God's sovereign will and purpose that's being accomplished in all
of this. He's the one choosing, predestining, putting his great plan into motion, accomplishing
his plans. He's doing that, and at the same time, we have a real response, that when we hear and
believe this gospel of our salvation, that that is a real and meaningful choice that we're making to
hear and believe. But the Bible is also very clear that we ourselves would never believe and choose
faith in the gospel on our own. It is only because of the grace of God, however you want to understand
that, that the grace of God works empowering our belief and trust in Jesus Christ and his work for
us. So all of these things are coming together, right? And all of this is coming together,
yes, for our salvation, yes, to guarantee us this inheritance, but we're not actually the ultimate
center and end of the story. What we find out as both these parallel lines conclude is that this
is to the praise of his glory, to the praise of his glory, right? We need to understand this
Because we so often think of ourselves
with this kind of main character energy
where we're like, everything's about me.
Everything's about my life.
Everything's about what I'm gonna do.
Everything's about how my life is going to go.
But we're being told here,
well, God is doing all these things for us,
out of love for us in Jesus Christ.
He's giving us this inheritance.
Ultimately, the purpose is actually to bring praise
and honor and glory to God
for everything that he has done.
it's ultimately about his glory. So if I can kind of sum up all of this here together, it's that
through faith in Jesus, we receive an inheritance that was obtained by Christ's sacrifice, is
guaranteed by the Holy Spirit, and is according to God's will and purpose for his glory. That's
like just a quick summary of everything we're talking about in this passage today. But as we
think about this, I don't want us to just stop at these beautiful truths that we're looking at here.
I don't want us to just stop and say, okay, I understand the idea.
Let's go ahead and move on.
How do these truths actually change the way we know and have a relationship with God
and how we live our lives on a daily basis?
This is where the rubber meets the road for us.
Because God doesn't want us to be people that just kind of have great knowledge.
He wants us to be people who are living in this active relationship with Him,
that through relationship with Jesus, we're becoming more like Jesus,
that as we become more like Jesus,
we're living out his calling and purpose for our lives.
All of this can only happen
as we live in this loving, trusting relationship
with God the Father.
How do these truths actually translate into that
for you and I?
I think there's something that's interesting
when you think about everything
we've just been talking about here.
This means that each of us here
is extraordinarily wealthy.
I don't know if you've really thought about that before.
Dave was challenging us with that
during opening worship time.
Like, let's reflect on that,
how the lavishness of God's love, right?
That lavishness, like generosity, abundance.
Like, man, when this says
that we have this inheritance,
that we've been blessed
according to the riches of God's grace
with all of his spiritual resources
of his eternal kingdom,
that we now share an inheritance,
not just with each other
and not even just with Apostle Paul,
but because we are in Christ,
we're sharing the inheritance of Christ.
that we actually receive all of those riches, all of that abundance,
that means you and I are incredibly wealthy.
Turn to someone next to you and say, you're rich.
Now that's great news, isn't it? Amen?
Man, that's great news.
But let's pause and think about this for a second.
Because when we look at our lives, our society, our culture,
here in the present world that we live in,
people have some kind of negative associations with being extraordinarily wealthy, don't they?
When you think about maybe somebody who's like a super multi-billionaire, I think a lot of times
people have some pretty strong judgments and opinions about people with that kind of wealth,
people with hundreds of millions, billions of dollars, just wealthy beyond belief. I don't think
we tend to think super positively of people with that kind of wealth, do we? So what does that mean
for us, receiving this inheritance, now being these newfound, super wealthy spiritual people?
What does that mean for us? I think there's actually a fascinating parallel here in how people
actually grow up with extreme wealth in this present world and actually how we relate with
God. So if you'll let me for a second, I'm going to kind of take a little detour. It's going to be
kind of a long one, but I'm going to bring us back, okay? So think about this for a second.
Think about the symptoms of affluent youth that we tend to see. And by the way, I did a little
reading and research on this. There are some great social science researchers who study affluent youth
and the effects of growing up with extreme wealth.
So there's some really great studies and information out there that I was looking into.
And just this question, like, what happens to a young person's development
when they grow up in a really wealthy family?
What happens?
And I think a lot of us have some assumptions about that,
maybe some stereotypes that we would use.
But here I'm trying to share, like, this is what people actually who study this stuff have found.
And obviously each person is unique,
but there are some common symptoms and risks of a kid growing up in an extremely wealthy family.
extremely wealthy parents, okay? What are some of the things that tend to be kind of some common
symptoms and risks? Well, it's pretty common to see elevated depression and anxiety that's driven
by academic and social pressure. Pretty common. And that kind of makes sense. Kids growing up,
they're around their parents and their parents' social circle, where maybe everybody's extremely
wealthy, successful, accomplished, kind of in the highest levels of society. That's a lot of
pressure that that young person might feel it. Oh, man, I have to meet up to that. I have to achieve
that. I have to get into that program and go to that school and get that job and be successful
the way that all my peers are, right? It's a lot of pressure. And by the way, that a lot of times
leads to things like self-medication and substance abuse, just to try to alleviate that pressure.
So, a lot of like drug and alcohol abuse. By the way, here, hopefully you'll notice these are not
things that are unique to wealthy youth. Like, I actually think that the vast majority of people
find ways to self-medicate. Maybe for an affluent teenager, they have financial resources to, like,
get a hold of alcohol or drugs in some way and get out of the consequences of it. For others of us,
maybe it's more through things like food, like just overeating to eating your feelings kind of
thing, or even stuff like pornography, maybe stuff like just screen time, just, man, endless
scrolling, just to escape, to self-medicate, to get that dopamine hit in our brains, right? Humans do
this, not just rich teenagers, okay? So, like, be aware of that as we look at this. So, there's
depression, anxiety, that pressure, oh my gosh, many of us feel that pressure. We have to meet
up somehow. Another thing would be, like, learned helplessness due to parental intervention.
Very common thing.
When mom and dad get rid of all struggles for you.
When mom and dad come along and, you know,
basically make sure that you never have to face any friction,
you never have to struggle,
never have to fight your way through, persevere through something.
Mom and dad take care of all the issues.
Mom and dad maybe even get rid of legal problems.
Well, there's a learned helplessness that comes from that.
And for many youth growing up in this environment,
it leads to this existential vacuum
where you question whether your accomplishments are truly yours or whether mom and dad just bought
them. You know, did I get great grades at that private school because I worked really hard or
because mom and dad funded the new wing of the gym, right? Like, you're always questioning that.
Like, am I, you know, all that kind of stuff, right? Another thing that tends to be,
tends to come with that would be moral impunity due to absence of consequences.
so again if mom and dad use their position their resources to get you out of trouble at school to
get you out of legal problems to get you out of the consequences of your actions that can lead to uh
to lead to this moral impunity basically saying i i don't think i'm ever going to be responsible
for anything and in fact i don't even know what right and wrong is because mom and dad just get
me out of those consequences another that can be pretty common is attachment deficit and emotional
distance. So, think about parents who maybe are very busy traveling the world, chairing boards,
doing all the stuff. That can lead to relational distrust and an inability to be emotionally
vulnerable and form deep relationships with other people because the sense that, like,
all relationships are temporary and transactional and no one's really around for you all the time.
These can all add up to a lot, okay? And this is just some stuff that, you know, that is seen,
but I'm trying to paint a little bit of a picture for us. If I give you one example of this,
some of you might remember this story from 2013, 13 years ago now. This young man named Ethan Couch,
I don't know if any of you remember his story, but when he was 16 years old in 2013, he'd just
gotten his driver's license, and he drank and drove with a blood alcohol content three times
the legal limit. He got in a crash and he killed four people. He was put on trial as an adult for
this crime, and in court, his lawyer presented an affluenza defense. Some of you might remember
that. They said because of his affluent upbringing, Ethan experienced impaired moral development
because his wealthy parents didn't enforce boundaries. They conditioned him to believe
money bought freedom from consequences. And wouldn't you know it, Ethan did not get any
jail time for his crime. Instead, he was given probation. And as soon as he got out on probation,
he fled to Mexico with his mom. Pretty sad story. When you think about this,
like it's, I mean, think about this idea of being spoiled.
That word spoiled. Like vegetables spoil. The idea of like a life made in the image of God,
valuable, valuable, having potential to represent God, having potential to live in loving relationship
with God, having potential to make a positive difference on the world, spoiled, spoiled,
right? This is a pretty bleak picture, but also as I share this, as we think about this, and again,
we'll come back eventually, don't worry, I'll connect the dots, but as we think about this,
We should also realize it is possible to raise a child in a healthy way, whether they're
in a wealthy environment or whatever kind of background.
So think instead about what healthy parenting might look like that might kind of go a little
different direction than what we talked about earlier.
What could raising a child in a healthy way look like, whether that's a wealthy child
or not?
Okay, so here are a few things.
Unconditional love rather than conditional approval.
Every kid wants this.
this is a decoupling love and acceptance from performance and achievement so mom and dad loving
little boy little girl loving their children not because they achieve not because they met up to
the performance pressure and standards but love because of that love relationship of parents and
children this is an incredibly valuable thing it relieves that anxiety and fear of failure
because, okay, I might fail, I might fall short, but I know mom and dad love me. How about firm
and forced boundaries? These are really important. When children experience firm and forced
boundaries, well, then the parents show that there are clear limits, and they especially don't rescue
their kids from the consequences of their actions. It's huge. The parents actually let their kids
face the consequences of what goes wrong, of their mistakes, but are there for them, loving them,
walking with them, and showing them what those boundaries and those limits are. Another would be
real household responsibilities. So kids grow up learning that they are contributors, they're
producers in the household, they have a meaningful role, they're not just consumers of mom and dad's
resources, but they help, they contribute, they're part of that family that builds perseverance,
that builds belonging, that builds a sense that my life can make a difference on the lives of others
as well, along with that encouraging creative risk without fear of personal ruin. What does that mean
that like the knowledge that your family is backing you up, and whether that's a wealthy family,
poor family, whatever they're saying, hey, mom and dad are with you. We're here, and our resources,
whatever they are, whether they're little or much, our family, we're here. Our presence, our love,
our resources, everything. We're behind you, so take some risks. Don't just play it safe. Choose
to do something positive with your life, and especially using resources and influence to serve.
Again, whether that's much or whether that's little. Say, whatever we've been given,
whatever we've been trusted with, to use that to serve others, because your life is not just about
you. Your life is intended to be for a greater purpose, to make a difference in the lives of
those around you. Now, why am I sharing all of this? Partly, I mean, just generally, parenting,
growing up as a kid, these are big things that affect us a lot. I partially share this knowing
that we've got a good chunk of parents in the room today. And for many of us, we need to be
thinking about, how can I be purposeful in raising my kids? And how especially does the gospel shape
my parenting so that my kids grow up knowing the love of mom and dad, that this is a love that is
there for them, that there's a love that is not conditioned upon performance, but this is a love
that is rooted in the grace and love of the gospel of Jesus Christ. Those things are really huge,
and parents, we should be thoughtful and have meaningful conversations and pray through and
think about how are we raising our kids to point them to Jesus Christ through even the way that we
raise them. That's huge. For some of you here, you're not parents yet. Maybe you will be one day,
But you have to process your own upbringing.
Why did I go through what I went through growing up?
Why did my parents raise me the way that they did?
Maybe what were the things my parents did that were really helpful?
Maybe there's some things, no parent is perfect.
Parents, by the way, you're standing before God is not based on you being a good parent.
It's the grace and love of Jesus, okay?
So parents, you don't have to be crushed.
You're going to fail as a parent.
I've failed as a parent.
Every parent fails and falls short.
Every one.
But even for kids, when we look at our parents and realize,
man, yeah, maybe my parents didn't know how this would affect me.
But how can I bring that to the Lord and say,
God, I want to process that through the gospel and see redemption and healing,
even reconciliation within my family.
These are important things for all of us.
But most of the reason I share this today, connecting with our passage,
is that we need to realize that God is a wise and loving Father.
That's the big thing that we need to realize today.
That for us, growing up now in a wealthy spiritual family,
we have struggles with this in our relationship with God.
We don't know how this inheritance is supposed to affect us.
And even God, what are you trying to do with all of this?
How should I deal with this idea that I have this massive, lavish inheritance
waiting for me in the kingdom of God?
How should that affect my life? And how can I look to you, God, as a wise and loving father
who is trying to lead me through all of this? Recognize, as we've seen in Ephesians here,
this idea according to the counsel of his will, that God knows what he is doing when he wants to
raise us to maturity in Christ. And here's where some of us struggle with that. Some of us struggle
deeply with this and we ask questions like, if God is so powerful and so loving and so good,
and if I'm supposed to have this great inheritance, well, why doesn't God just fix all my problems
then? God, I'm praying. I'm praying and I'm praying for this problem to go away. So God,
why don't you just make my problems go away? Maybe we even wrestle with this idea of like,
why do I have to face the consequences of my actions then? Because if Jesus died on the cross,
shed his blood, so now I'm forgiven. Now, my inheritance is forgiveness in Jesus Christ. My
inheritance is that I'm an adopted son or daughter of God. I'm received. Even though I've done the
worst sins, I'm received and loved and accepted by him. Well, then why do I still have to face
consequences for what I'm doing? God, shouldn't you just kind of get rid of all that, wipe all
that away? Why don't I get all the benefits now of this inheritance? Why do I have to wait
for later? We might start feeling a little bit prodigal son-ish with that. God, I want the
inheritance now. I want all of it now, all the benefits now. Why doesn't God just give that to
us? Why do we only have the down payment now, the guarantee now, but the fullness is later?
why should i have to take responsibility and serve man god you're so wealthy god you got all
the resources of your heavenly kingdom why should i have to do anything can't i just enjoy can't i
just be kind of a passive family member what's the point of all of this and by the way i should
mention for some of us i mean i'm sharing all of these struggles we may have for some of us i don't
want to make light of the struggles we have. Because for some of us, we have really deep and
painful experiences in our lives that we're genuinely bringing to God and saying, God, why?
God, why did I go through this? God, why did this happen to me? Maybe it's even something in your
family with your parents. God, why? And we struggle with that. That's a real struggle we can and should
bring to God, and I'm not making light of that at all. The question I have for us in all of this
is how do we actually relate with God with those struggles here? And I think for some of us,
what we effectively are thinking and asking is, God, if I have such a great inheritance,
why won't you just go ahead and spoil me now? Why won't you just go ahead and just give me
everything I want right now. Why, God? And here's the answer. It's that God wants to raise children
who are secure and confident in the love, in the presence, in the future inheritance,
in all the promises of his kingdom, but not kids who are spoiled or self-centered.
that's God's counsel of his will his purpose he is so wise in raising us and I think back on my
life now and I think about so many things I've gone through where I had to go through seasons of
deep struggle in my faith but as I talked about earlier when parents remove all the struggle from
their kid's life and just use their resources and use their influence to remove those struggles
that kid never matures and grows up. They remain a perpetual child or adolescent.
Going through those struggles, God was so wise in my life because through that I matured and I grew
and I learned to trust God more. So many times when I prayed and I prayed, God, why don't you
just take away this struggle in my life? And much like God told Apostle Paul, God often responds,
my grace is sufficient for you. My power is made perfect in weakness. I want you to discover that,
to see that, to learn that.
And so when we look at all of this here,
what God wants for us and wants for us so deeply
is that we would be secure in his love
and acceptance given purely by his grace,
that we'd be confident because we know
we have an eternal inheritance that is waiting for us,
that's secure, that's guaranteed by the Holy Spirit,
that we'd be mature because we still face
the reality and consequences of sin
and we go through struggles,
but we learn to trust God through those times,
that we're free and bold because our sins have been redeemed and atoned for by Jesus Christ,
that we're empowered and confident because the Holy Spirit is always with us
through every struggle that we face and that we have purpose in our lives
because we're living for something greater than ourselves.
This is God's plan and purpose for us.
He doesn't want to raise a bunch of spoiled kids waiting for their eternal inheritance.
He wants to raise a bunch of kids who know they're loved, who know God is with them no matter what,
and who are secure because we know we don't have to earn or achieve or prove or perform to get
God's eternal inheritance, that that's given to us purely by God's grace. He wants us to be so
secure in that that we can then live boldly for his kingdom. And brothers and sisters,
the more that we recognize this, the more that we live in these truths, well then that should
lead us to worship, to the praise of his glory. Wow, God, instead of doubting your character,
doubting your plan, doubting your whatever, now, God, I can see you're so wise. You're so all-knowing.
God, your plans are so good, so perfect, and I can't see everything right now. I can't understand
everything right now, but, God, I know your plan has gone from before the beginning of time to the
end of time itself, and, God, you're going to bring everything to completion. You're going to
bring me to that heavenly home. You're going to make all things new. God, I can live knowing that
truth and worshiping you and rejoicing in you and adoring you and living in that love relationship
with you because of it. This is God's heart and will for us, brothers and sisters, and we have
that down payment of our inheritance in the Holy Spirit. Our full inheritance is in the world to
come in the kingdom of God, but the Holy Spirit now lives within us. And this is something I think
I would pray and desire for our church to live in the reality of more and more.
To know that the Holy Spirit, the book of Romans chapter 8 tells us,
it is by the Spirit of God living within us that we cry, Abba, Father.
That we cry out to the Father, we can be secure in that relationship with Him.
Because His Holy Spirit is a seal and a guarantee upon our hearts of the inheritance that we have.
what would our lives look like
if we lived
in this truth, in this trust
in this reality
what would it look like to give boldly
and confidently
because we know we have this
secure inheritance
that God is always with us
as we go through the trials and the struggles
that he has a purpose for our lives
how would worship then overflow
from our lives because we're living in
and discovering and experiencing that reality
That's where if I could sum today's message up with the one thing, it's to live with security
and confidence because of your inheritance in Christ. To live with security and confidence
because of your inheritance in Christ. And as you think about this, I really want us to dig into
our relationship with God today. God the Father who's accomplishing his plan and purpose.
Jesus Christ the Son who gave his life on the cross to obtain that inheritance for us. God the
Holy Spirit who is alive in us, who is giving, who is stealing and securing and guaranteeing
that inheritance for us? Can we dig in in relationship with Him? And here's some questions
I'd love us to reflect on here this morning. First, are your security and value rooted in Jesus or in
something else? I think for a lot of us, this is where the rubber meets the road. What makes us
feel secure? Where do we try to find confidence? You know, I think there's a whole world out there
of like kind of modern self-help
where I've seen YouTube videos about this,
books about this,
where it's like look in the mirror
and tell yourself I'm confident,
I'm capable, I'm strong,
I know it, I know my stuff,
like all that stuff.
And man, I don't know about you,
I find trying to find confidence in myself
and my own abilities is crushing.
That's where that pressure comes on hard, doesn't it?
That's what we try to escape from with self-medicating.
That's not hope.
That's not life.
All that is is pressure.
Can we step back from that and say,
God, I've been trying to be confident in myself.
Lord, help me be confident in you
and the gospel of my salvation instead.
Secondly, do you trust your wise and loving Father
to mature you through trials and difficulties?
Do you trust God to mature you
through trials and difficulties?
Because he's wise, he's loving.
Again, spoiling us is not a good solution.
I know it looks like the easy way out.
God, why don't you just get rid of my problems?
God, why don't you get rid of my struggles?
God, why don't you just remove the trials from my life?
God loves us too much for that.
His wisdom is too great for that.
He lets us go through some of those things
in the broken, fallen world we live in
because by going through those things,
learning to trust him through it,
we mature, we grow, our character grows,
our hope grows. We thrive, actually, as we go through those trials, trusting in God.
And thirdly, how would confidence in your inheritance through the Holy Spirit change
your life? If you could be truly confident in this inheritance, that inheritance, it's waiting
for me. That inheritance, it's secure. It's guaranteed. It's sealed in my heart as I respond
by grace to the message of the gospel.
God, it's secure.
How would that security, that confidence change your life?
What bold steps of faith would you start to take?
How much joy would overflow?
How much assurance would you have
going through trials and uncertainty?
How much hope would you have?
What good fruit would start to overflow from your life
if you could be that confident
in your inheritance in Jesus Christ.
These are things we can come to God now
and pray for and seek God for.
And I would even encourage some of you,
maybe a good thing to think about this week
is like, could I maybe identify
one area of your life
where you've been relying on your performance
rather than your inheritance?
And just surrender that to God.
Say, God, this new week,
as I wake up on Monday morning,
I want to surrender this to you, God.
I've been trusting in.
I've been trusting in myself, trusting in my own ability, my own performance.
God, help me to surrender that as I start this new week
and trust and find my security, my confidence, my hope,
and the inheritance I have in Jesus Christ.
How would that start to change things?
I want us to be able to respond today
and to respond really by coming to God,
coming to God in trust, coming to God in assurance, coming to God seeking hope, seeking confidence in
him. And you know, brothers and sisters, this is something else I think it really happens
as we come to God in worship. There's a reason that Paul is bringing this in again and again
to the praise of his glorious grace, to the praise of his glorious grace. There's a reason
this is coming in. It's because what we're made for and where we find a real foundation and secure
hope is when we live in the way we're made to live, which is in loving, adoring, worshiping
relationship with God. And so I'd love to just come to God and respond that way to Him today.
We've got our questions. We've got our struggles. God, why this? Why am I struggling with that? Why
this? But the answer to that is not in trying to figure it all out, because we won't be able to
fully in this lifetime? The answer to that is actually coming to our wise and loving Father
and approaching Him in worship and seeing that He is greater, His will is greater, His plan is
greater than all those things that we wrestle with and struggle with. And so can we stand
together and we'll spend some time in response today?